Guide to the Mildred Rackley Simon Papers ALBA.097
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Mildred Rackley Simon Papers
1937-1938
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Simon, Mildred Rackley, 1906-2003
ALBA.097
0.5 Linear Feet (1 box)
Mildred Rackley Simon (1906-1992) was a secretary/interpreter and hospital administrator during the Spanish Civil War, working for the American Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy. The bulk of this collection consists of correspondence between Rackley, Doctors Edward Barsky and Irving Busch, and other medical personnel. Also included are administrative reports and documents from the Spanish Civil War era.
Provenance
The Mildred Rackley Simon Papers collection came to New York University in January 2001 as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly housed at Brandeis University.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Historical/Biographical Note
Mildred Rackley Simon (1906-1992) was born in Carlsbad, New Mexico into a ranching family. After attending for one year at the University of Texas in Austin, Rackley received a teaching degree from the Las Vegas Normal School. In 1927, Rackley moved to Taos where she taught high school. She also began painting and drawing with the encouragement of Walter Ufer, prominent German painter and member of the Taos Society of Artists. Rackley became involved in the artists' colony, and the community sparked international awareness and political consciousness in Rackley that influenced her in later years.
After marrying the German painter Hans Paap, Rackley traveled throughout Europe with her husband to study art history. She eventually settled in 1931 on the Spanish island of Malorca, and she witnessed the jubilation of the Spaniards following the overthrow of the monarchy and creation of the Spanish Republic. Settlement in Malorca also placed Rackley in contact with German refugees, for whom she did translation work as a supplementary job. Rackley's marriage soon ended, and she returned to Taos to continue her studies in drawing and painting.
Longing for a broader artistic and cultural community, Rackley moved to New York City in 1935. She found work at Fight Magazine, a publication of the League against War and Fascism. When her job ended at the magazine, she began work for the Artists' Union, a group that pressured the Works Progress Administration (WPA) to support unemployed artists. She became the head of the unemployment section of the union and later the vice-president. It was during this time that Rackley became acquainted with Dr. Edward Barsky, the doctor who led the first American medical units into Spain during the Spanish Civil War. Dr. Barsky asked Rackley, who spoke fluent Spanish, German, and French, if she would serve as secretary/interpreter for the American Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy in Spain. Rackley agreed to go, and in January 1937 she sailed to Spain on the S.S. Paris.
Rackley helped to set up hospitals in Valdeganga, Hueta, Romeral, and Villa Paz. Her duties included fulfilling administrative tasks, communicating with the Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy in New York, and locating food and supplies for hospital staff and patients. She also aided in the hospital evacuations to Barcelona in the spring of 1938. Rackley generally served as Dr. Barsky's confidential administrative assistant. In the summer of 1938, Rackley and the rest of the American medical unit discontinued service, and Rackley returned to the United States aboard the S.S. Aquinata in June 1938.
During World War II, Rackley worked for Moore Drydock shipyards in Oakland, California, where she did drafting and designing. She also helped organize the shipyards for union recognition. After the company refused to hire one of her friends on the basis of race, Rackley quit Moore Drydock and began working for Kaiser Shipyards. In 1944 Rackley married Rawlings Simon with whom she eventually adopted two sons, Phillip and John. After the war, the Simons settled in Northern California where she was an active member of the Bay Area VALB Post. By 1960, she had returned to teaching. Mildred Rackley Simon died in California in 1992.
Scope and Content Note
Series I, Correspondence, 1937-1938, consists of letters written by Rackley and other medical personnel. Most of the letters contain administrative information. Included are letters in which Rackely describes the hospital setting and duties, most notably to the "Friends" at the American Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy in New York. In the letters she gives detailed accounts of the medical personnel stationed at the Madrid Front, including Dr. Irving Busch, a prominent physician, and Florence Pike, the head nurse from Canada. The series also contains a letter from Rackley to Dr. Edward Barsky, a physician who led the American medical personnel to Spain and for whom Rackley worked. There are multiple letters addressed to Dr. Irving Busch from other physicians and medical personnel, and an anonymous letter from a patient.
Series II, Subject Files, 1937-1938, consists of administrative reports, ward schedules, instructions for hospital evacuation, and a list of medical bureau personnel. Also included is a questionnaire on the quality of hospital life and the anonymous answers and comments from hospital staff. This series contains Rackley's identification cards and memorabilia from her time in Spain including a Barcelona city map and Spanish versed song sheets.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically within each series.
Organized into 2 Series:
Missing Title
I. Correspondence, 1937-1938.
II. Subject Files, 1937-1938.
Related Material at the Tamiment Library/Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Toby Jensky and Philip Schachter Papers, ALBA #55
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Edward K. Barsky Papers, ALBA #125
Fredericka Martin Papers, ALBA #1
Frances Patai Papers, ALBA #131
Separated Material
Photographs from the Mildred Rackley Simon Collection have been transferred to the non-print section of the ALBA collection in the Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives.
Correspondence.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Women.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Hospitals.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939.; Medical records.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American.; Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy; Simon, Mildred Rackley, 1906-2003; Medical Bureau and North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; Barsky, Edward K., 1895-1975; Spain. Ejercito Popular de la Republica. Brigada Internacional, XV; North American Committee to Aid Spanish Democracy; Busch, Irving
- Series I, Correspondence, 1937-1938
  - Barsky, Dr. Edward: Invitation to Farewell Dinner, Oct 27, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Busch, Dr. Irving: Correspondence, Jun 1937-Nov 1937 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Hart, Alexander to Barsky, Dr. Edward, Dec 1937-Apr 1938 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - [?], Joe to Rackley (Simon), Mildred, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Medical Bureau to Aid Spanish Democracy to Busch, Dr. Irving, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Navarro, Jose to Telge, Oskar, Sep 28, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Pieters, C.: Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Rackley (Simon), Mildred: Correspondence, Sep 1937-Nov 1937 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Rackley (Simon), Mildred: Memoir, Dec 10, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Taina, Wayne to Telge, Oskar, Oct 1, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Thompson, David to Rackley (Simon), Mildred, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Van Zant, Frances to Rackley (Simon), Mildred, Apr 21, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Vogel, Dr. Sidney Leon to Busch, Dr. Irving, Aug 1937-Nov 1937 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Freed, Rose and Kornblum, Morris to American Medical Bureau, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Series II, Subject Files, 1937-1938
  - Administrative Reports, undated, Aug 1937-Dec 1937 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Barcelona: City Map, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Clippings: Barsky on Spanish Civil War, Jul 1937 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Clippings: Medical Unit Personnel, undated, Jan 1937 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Evacuation of Hospital to Barcelona: Notes, Spring 1938 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Medical Bureau Personnel: List of Names, undated (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Questionnaire and Answers: Suggestions for Improving Hospital Life, undated (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Rackley (Simon), Mildred: Identification Documents, undated, Apr 1937-Jul 1938 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Rackley (Simon), Mildred: Notebooks (2), Apr 1938-Jul 1938 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Rackley (Simon), Mildred: Salvo Conductos, Jul 1937-Jul 1938 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Song sheets, undated (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Ward Schedules, undated, Aug 18, 1937-Aug 25, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 26)